Will T. Hale papers, 1900-1962 C358
Indiana University Archives
Will T. Hale papers
1900-1962
Indiana University Archives
Hale, Will T. (Will Taliaferro), 1880-1967
C358
1 cubic foot 1 box
With a focus on Biblical literature and Victorian poetry, Will T. Hale was a professor of English Literature at Indiana University from 1913-1950. Included in this collection are correspondence, journals, engagement calendars, and teaching materials, such as lesson plans and notes.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Advance notice is required for access.
Biographical Note
Will T. Hale was born in Mobile, Alabama in 1880 to Foster Kirksey and Nettie Pope Hale. Developing an early appreciation for English literature, he graduated from his local high school in 1898 and then began his collegiate education by first attending Vanderbilt University where he earned his A.B. and A.M. degrees in 1902. He then proceeded to Yale University where he graduated with his Bachelors from the School of Divinity in 1905. After this, he began his teaching career when he became a professor of History and English at Morrisville College in Montana for a short period before moving on to the University of Texas, where he was an instructor of English from 1907-1910. Soon after, he obtained his Masters degree in English at Columbia University and graduated in 1912. He returned to Yale for his Ph.D., and graduated in 1914. His career at Indiana University began as an English instructor in 1913 and in 1918, he became an assistant professor. In 1924, he was promoted to associate professor and in 1929, he became a full professor. During his career, he specialized in Victorian poetry and Bible literature. He published and edited several books about popular authors, such as Brontë and Milton. He was also active in the fraternity Phi Gamma Delta, which he joined during his college years and as a faculty member, he aided the house in events and fundraising. Though only barely mentioned in biographical material, it is said he regularly helped young men complete college through monetary grants and offering room and board at his house.
During his tenure at IU, Hale was regularly awarded the Brown Derby award, which was given to the most popular professor of the year. He was a member of the American Association of University Professors and the Modern Languages Association of America and the Faculty Club at IU. On a more personal level, he established the Browning Club of Indiana University and was a Mason for many years. He retired on July 1, 1950 but stayed active in the community as well as IU until his death on February 5, 1967.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: Journals, Notes, Personal files, and Teaching materials. All files are arranged alphabetically by folder title and all records within are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into four series: Journals, Notes, Personal files, and Teaching materials.
Journals include a day-to-day listing of what Hale bought, who he talked to, and many other details about his personal life. This was especially consistent during the years 1957 to 1962.
The Notes series includes Hale's notes from his college and graduate school years. These also include his interpretation of certain poems and views on their authors.
Personal files include Professor Hale's correspondence, engagement calendars and journals. The latter of which also include his records of weather and sport scores. Also in this series are materials about the house the professor built along with information and samples of how he decorated. Included also are Hale's notes and writings from when he was a student.
Teaching materials include lesson plans, papers on assignment format, and notebooks that include notes on his students.
Acquisition Information
9010, 9011, 9023
Appraisal
Duplicates removed. Non-Indiana University yearbooks pulled and offered to appropriate school repositories. Grades removed. Hale sometimes kept personal notes regarding his students and their religions, etc. These were removed.
Literature teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives; Bible and literature --Study and teaching (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington; Hale, Will T. (Will Taliaferro), 1880-1967 -- Archives; Hale, Will T. (Will Taliaferro), 1880-1967 -- Correspondence
- Journals, 1900-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1962, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Records, 1957-1960 (Box 1)
    General
    (includes weather reports and correspondence log)
- Notes, 1900-1918
  - 1900-1918, (10 folders) (Box 1)
- Personal files, 1900-1963
  - "A book of rhymes", November 1907 (Box 1)
  - The Browning Society at Indiana University, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1958 (Box 1)
  - Engagement calendars, 1946-1963; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Materials on Hale's house being built and decorated, undated (Box 1)
  - Student writings, 1900-1912 (Box 1)
- Teaching Materials, 1937-1958
  - Lesson plans, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes and final exams, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Elementary composition - C101 & W103, undated (Box 1)
  - Syllabus and exams - L367 & L368 - Literature of the Bible II, undated (Box 1)
  - Shakespeare - C254b, undated (Box 1)
  - Schedule (Box 1)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 1)